בוקר טוב. Boker tov.
So today's דף daf is
נ"ב nun bet and we pick up a little bit in. We're
actually in the middle of figuring out these הלכות halachot about the
חטאת khatas and that the remainder of the blood is spilled on
the outer מזבח mizbayach even about an inner חטאת. khatas. And we
had a debate about רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva and רבי ישמעאל Rebbe
Ishmael sort of making this argument from a קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
The argument according to רש"י Rashi was that you don't need a
פסוק pasuk to tell you that you throw the blood of an
outer חטאת khatas or any outer sacrifice I should say because outer
חטאת khatas you don't throw the blood. You put it on all
four corners. But when you throw the blood of an עולה ola
and a שלמים shlamim and any of the outer sacrifices that you
do it at the corners that have a base opposite them as
opposed to, you know, here's the the southeast corner which does not
have a base opposite to it. And they said you don't need
a פסוק pasuk to know that because you make it a קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. And what was the קל וחומר? kal vachomer? The
קל וחומר kal vachomer was that if the blood is actually, you
know, spilled on that well let
that blood which is not coming to do an atonement, meaning the
remnant of the blood is spilled at the base, then certainly blood
that's coming to do atonement, the initial placing of blood has to
be at a corner that has a base below it. Okay that
which is a little bit of a funny קל וחומר kal vachomer
but that was their קל וחומר. kal vachomer. And then the question
was was that well רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva and רבי ישמעאל Rebbe
Ishmael sounded like they were saying pretty much the same thing, what
was the difference between them? So the גמרא Gemara said well maybe
the difference between them was whether or not, even though רבי ישמעאל
Rebbe Ishmael said that the blood that spilled is not coming to
atone, it doesn't achieve atonement, maybe he says it's actually מעכב, me'akev,
it's required by an inner חטאת. khatas. So maybe it prevents the
inner חטאת khatas from being valid. We have not seen that yet.
I mean well we saw it earlier in the גמרא Gemara but
in this פרק perek we haven't seen it. In this פרק perek
in our משנה mishna it said that the spilling of the blood
even by an inner חטאת khatas is not מעכב, me'akev, does not
prevent it from being valid. But because רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva and
רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Ishmael sounded like they were saying almost the exact
same thing that the spilling of the blood is not מכפר, mechaper,
one suggestion the גמרא Gemara had about how they're differing is that
maybe although רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Ishmael is saying it doesn't atone, it
still is מעכב. me'akev. So that's where we left off with yesterday.
So we pick up in the middle of נ"ב עמוד א' nun
bet amud aleph and it says like this: איכא בינייהו מר סבר
מעכב ומר סבר לא מעכב. Ika beynaihu mar savar me'akev umar savar
lo me'akev. The line starts with the word מעכב me'akev about twenty
lines down. רב פפא אמר Rav Papa amar now רב פפא Rav
Papa says דכולי עלמא שיירים אין מעכבין. dechulei alma shirayim ein me'akvim.
No,
even רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Ishmael would hold that the spilling of the
blood even of an inner חטאת khatas is not מעכב. me'akev. So
then how are they differing? They're sounding like they're saying almost the
exact same thing. והכא במיצוי חטאת העוף קמיפלגי. Ve-hacha be-mitzuy khatas ha-of
k-miflagi.
They're discussing not the spilling of the blood of a חטאת, khatas,
but after you, you know, you sort of שחט shecht or whatever
do מליקה melikah on a חטאת העוף khatas ha-of and the blood
comes out of the neck, it says you squeeze the neck against
the side of the altar and והנשאר בדם ימצה אל קיר
המזבח ve-nish'ar ha-dam yimatzeh el kir ha-mizbayach what's left of the blood
you squeeze out against the side of the altar and then that
blood runs down the side of the altar. So is that מעכב?
me'akev? That's the debate. Okay so when they say that certain blood
of a חטאת khatas is not coming לכפר, le-khaper,
the spilling of the blood is not coming לכפר le-khaper when we
wanted to suggest that according to רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Ishmael maybe it
wasn't coming לכפר le-khaper the remaining of the spilling of the blood
but maybe it was מעכב. me'akev.
So רב פפא Rav Papa is here saying no that the basic
spilling of the blood of a חטאת khatas at the base is
not מעכב. me'akev. But maybe the squeezing out of the blood according
to רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Ishmael of the חטאת העוף khatas ha-of maybe
that would be מעכב. me'akev. Okay? Yes. Question on the חטאת khatas
was there a distinction made between the inner and the outer in
terms of whether or the completion has to be?
Yeah the suggestion that it would be מעכב me'akev would only be
for the inner because the outer even one of the four applications
בדיעבד bedi'avad you only need even one of only one of the
four applications.
So certainly the spilling of the blood is not מעכב. me'akev. The
possibility that the spilling of the blood for a חטאת khatas is
מעכב me'akev is only for an inner חטאת khatas where all the
applications are מעכב. me'akev. Okay but and here we're saying though maybe
everybody holds it's not מעכב me'akev but the question is when the
Torah describes how you do the bird חטאת, khatas, there we're not
really dealing with spilling at the base, we're dealing with a second
procedure, it says but it does say what remains squeeze out. So
is that telling you that that's necessary because it's sort of described
as what you do with the remains maybe it's not מעכב. me'akev.
Okay. והכא במיצוי חטאת העוף מעכב קמיפלגי. Ve-hacha be-mitzuy khatas ha-of me'akev
k-miflagi.
That's what they debate. מר סבר מעכב ומר סבר לא. Mar savar
me'akev umar savar lo. Okay. תניא כוותיה דרב פפא Tanya k-vatei de-Rav
Papa now we point like רב פפא Rav Papa not about the
issue about the blood of the bird but about the issue about
that they everybody basically agrees that
that the spilling of the blood of an inner חטאת khatas is
not מעכב. me'akev. Okay here's the ברייתא. baraita. ואת כל דם הפר...
Ve-et kol dam ha-par... ואת כל דם הפר ישפך. V'et kol dam
hapar yishapeich.
All the rest blood of the ox you shall pour out. This
is again by the פר כהן משיח, par kohen mashiach, one of
the inner חטאות. chatasot. Okay, at the base of the altar. מה
תלמוד לומר הפר? ma talmud lomar hapar? Why does it just say
ואת כל הדם ישפך? v'et kol hadam yishapeich? Why did it say
ואת כל דם הפר v'et kol dam hapar of the cow? That's
an extra word. We know we're dealing with a cow. So מה
תלמוד לומר הפר? ma talmud lomar hapar? לימד על פר יום הכיפורים
שטעון דמים ליסוד, limed al par Yom HaKippurim she'taun damim l'yesod, דברי
רבי. divrei Rabbi.
Because by Yom Kippur, which is an inner חטאת chatas and it,
you know, has all the applications on the כפורת, kaporet, the פרוכת,
parochet, the מזבח הזהב, mizbe'ach hazahav, and then you burn the meat
outside, it never says what you do with the remnant of the
blood. So since it says by the פר כהן משיח par kohen
mashiach spill the remnant of the blood at the base of the
outer altar and there it has the extra word פר, par, so
that's to tell you there's another פר par that you're also going
to spill the blood at the base of the altar, and what
is that? That's the פר par of Yom Kippur. Okay, so that's
what you learn from it, דברי רבי. divrei Rabbi. אמר רבי ישמעאל,
amar Rabbi Yishmael, says Rabbi Yishmael,
he's not disagreeing with Rabbi, he's just going to sort of point
out that there's a קל וחומר kal vachomer that you should know
that you would have to do this. What's the קל וחומר? kal
vachomer? הקל וחומר: hakal vachomer: ומה אם מי שאין נכנס דמו לפנים
חובה טעון יסוד.
uma im mi she'ein nichnas damo lifnim
chova taun yesod.
So the פר כהן משיח, par kohen mashiach, there's no obligation to
bring a פר כהן משיח, par kohen mashiach, meaning, it's when a
כהן גדול kohen gadol sins, hopefully you'll never have to bring it.
So you only bring it, it's referred to as a מצוה mitzvah
not a חובה. chova. Not a מצוה mitzvah like it's a מצוה
mitzvah to put on ציצית tzitzit or something. It's a מצוה mitzvah
meaning, in the right circumstances you have to do it. But you
don't have a fixed obligation, a regular obligation to bring the פר
par of the כהן גדול kohen gadol for sin, meaning, as opposed
to Yom Kippur. So this type of a פר כהן גדול par
kohen gadol which is not a strict obligation, not a regular obligation,
and nevertheless the Torah makes this demand, okay, so ומה
מי שאין נכנס דמו לפנים חובה טעון יסוד, uma mi she'ein nichnas
damo lifnim chova taun yesod, the Torah demands it be spilled at
the base. מי שנכנס דמו לפנים חובה, mi she'nichnas damo lifnim chova,
something like the פר par of Yom Kippur where it's obviously you
have to do it once a year, it's a strict
obligation, so that case אינו דין שטעון יסוד? eino din she'taun yesod?
How much more so should it require a base? So again he's
agreeing that the פר par of Yom Kippur needs a base, he's
just saying you could have figured it out from a קל וחומר,
kal vachomer, you didn't need the extra word פר. par. רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, again it's very interesting, Rabbi Akiva and Rabbi Yishmael basically
in multiple places here are doing the same דרשות drashot with slightly
different language. Okay, so Rabbi Akiva says I'll do I'll say that
even in a sharper way. אמר רבי עקיבא: amar Rabbi Akiva:
ומה מי שאין דמו טעון לפני ולפנים בין לחובה בין למצוה, uma
mi she'ein damo taun lifnai v'lifnim bein l'chova bein l'mitzvah, I'll make
another קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Not only is the פר יום כיפור
par Yom Kippur more weighty because it's a fixed obligation, it's more
weighty because it goes into the Holy of Holies. Okay, the blood
of a פר כהן משיח par kohen mashiach does not go to
the inner sanctum but not the, you know, you put it on
the פרוכת, parochet, on the מזבח הזהב, mizbe'ach hazahav, but it doesn't
go into the Holy of Holies. So that adds to the קל
וחומר. kal vachomer.
The כהן משיח kohen mashiach of the normal year if he sins,
it's not (A) it's not חובה, chova, it's not a standing obligation,
and (B) even when you deal with the blood, you don't bring
it in to the inner sanctum to the Holy of
Holies.
ומה מי שאין דמו נכנס לפני ולפנים, uma mi she'ein damo nichnas
lifnai v'lifnim, it doesn't go into the Holy of Holies, בין לחובה
בין למצוה bein l'chova bein l'mitzvah for any purpose, טעון יסוד taun
yesod and nevertheless you put you pour the remainder of the blood
on the base. מי שנכנס דמו חובה לפני ולפנים, mi she'nichnas damo
chova lifnai v'lifnim, so Yom Kippur it's weightier in two ways: number
one, weightier in the way that Rabbi Yishmael said, it's a standing
obligation, and number two, it's weightier in that it goes into the
Holy of Holies, so אינו דין שטעון יסוד? eino din she'taun yesod?
How much more so should it require a base? Okay, fine, so
they're saying you didn't need the פסוק pasuk פר par to tell
me on Yom Kippur you pour it at the base, you could
have learned it from a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. But now that
you have a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, we're going to ask the
following question.
Okay, יכול יעכבנו, yachol y'takeivenu,
because you know normally the principle is that the Torah has to
repeat it to say that it's מעכב, me'akeiv, right? Repeat a requirement.
But here the argument is, well maybe it's like it did repeat
a requirement. Why? Because I would have known from a קל וחומר
kal vachomer that you spill the blood of Yom Kippur at the
base of the outer altar. And never so I already knew that
הלכה. halacha. And nevertheless by that extra word הפר hapar that it
says by the כהן משיח, kohen mashiach, it's telling me that even
the פר par of Yom Kippur has to be spilled at the
base. So maybe that's a doubling and maybe that doubling is telling
me that at least by Yom Kippur the spilling of the blood
at the base is מעכב. me'akeiv.
יכול יעכבנו? yachol y'akeivenu? תלמוד לומר וכלה מכפר את הקודש. talmud lomar
v'chilah mikapeir et hakodesh. It says on Yom Kippur you complete doing
the atonement. וכלה מכפר את הקודש. v'chilah mikapeir et hakodesh. שלמו כל
הכפרות כולן, shalmu kol hakaparot kulan, דברי רבי ישמעאל. divrei Rabbi Yishmael.
Once the כפרות, kaparot, which are the placing of the blood on
the altar, that's identified as a כפרה, kapara, right? The spilling of
the blood at the base, even if it's מעכב, me'akeiv, we said
before is not מכפר, mechapeir, is not central to the atonement, it
might be necessary to make everything good but it's not an act
of atonement. So here it says וכלה מכפר v'chilah mikapeir and also
on Yom Kippur the only thing it explicitly mentions is the placing
on the altar and פרוכת parochet and Yom Kippur. or it doesn't
mention the spilling at the base. So when the verse on יום
כיפור Yom Kippur says if you're done doing the atonement, it means
done with the placing on the altar, the placing on the פרוכת.
parokhes. It doesn't mean the spilling. The spilling isn't atonement and it
isn't even mentioned by יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So that פסוק pasuk
makes it clear when you're done with the atoning acts, then you're
done, then you're יוצא. yotze. The spilling at the base is not
מעכב. me'akev. Okay. וכלה מכפר את הקודש, vekhila mikaper es hakodesh, שם
כל הכפרות כולן דברי רבי ישמעאל. sham kol hakapparos kulu divrei Rebbe
Yishmael. Now this is what proves Rav Hoff's point, because here you
have רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Yishmael saying that even though clearly you do
have to spill it at the base on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
it's not required for it to be valid. Once you've done all
the required acts of יום כיפור Yom Kippur that are mentioned there,
all the atoning acts, which does not include the spilling of the
blood, then you're done. Then you have fulfilled the קרבן. korban. Okay,
so here you see that for רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Yishmael even on
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, the spilling at the base is not מעכב.
me'akev. Now, קל וחומר לפר כהן משיח מעתה. kal vachomer le'par kohen
mashiach me'ata. Now, let's now that we made that argument by יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, we used a קל וחומר kal vachomer to argue
you knew you'd have to spill it at the base, but then
the extra word of פר par might have said it's a doubling
and maybe said it's מעכב, me'akev, and then רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Yishmael
says no, based on this verse, it's not מעכב me'akev by יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. So let's now have the same discussion by a
normal inner חטאת. chatas. Is the spilling of the blood מעכב? me'akev?
And we can make a similar type of an argument to at
least have a הוה אמינא hava amina to think that it would
be מעכב. me'akev. What's that argument? Okay, ומה מי שאין נכנס דמו
לפנים לא חובה ולא מצוה טעון יסוד. u'mah mi she'ein nichnas damo
lifnim lo chova velo mitzva taun yesod. So
here's the argument. If it's true that
the פר כהן גדול, par kohen gadol, which does not go in...
excuse me, if it's true that a normal חטאת, chatas, okay, a
normal outer חטאת chatas needs to be spilled at the base. The
same way we made a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, right? What was
our קל וחומר? kal vachomer? Right, because here by פר כהן משיח
par kohen mashiach it says
ואת דם הפר
ישפך,
ve'es dam
hapar yishapech, okay, this is פר כהן משיח. par kohen mashiach.
So we said הפר hapar is coming to tell me יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. But then we said, you know what? That's an extra
word and it's like a doubling for יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, and
maybe it means it's מעכב me'akev because by יום כיפור Yom Kippur
I could have made a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. If the כהן
משיח kohen mashiach needs a base and that's not a fixed obligation
and that doesn't go into the Holy of Holies, certainly יום כיפור
Yom Kippur does. So it has the extra word הפר, hapar, that's
like a doubling, and that might tell you it's מעכב. me'akev. And
then the word וכלה מכפר את הקודש vekhila mikaper es hakodesh told
you it's not מעכב me'akev by יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So now
similarly we're going to say that you can make the same קל
וחומר kal vachomer by this itself because a normal חטאת chatas it
says spill the blood at the base. So if for a normal
חטאת chatas you spill the blood at the base and a normal
חטאת chatas doesn't go into the holies, this which does go into
the holies, not the Holy of Holies but it goes into the
holies, so it's that much holier, certainly you should spill the blood
at the base. So why does it say spill the blood at
the base by a normal פר כהן משיח? par kohen mashiach? If
I could have learned it from a קל וחומר kal vachomer from
an outer חטאת? chatas? Maybe I should read that as a doubling,
and maybe by reading that as a doubling I'm going to say
it's מעכב. me'akev. So it's a similar type of use a קל
וחומר kal vachomer to say that this verse is like a doubling
and it's מעכב, me'akev, and then we're going to tell me it's
not מעכב. me'akev. Okay, so let's take a look. ומה מי שאין
נכנס דמו לפנים, u'mah mi she'ein nichnas damo lifnim, a normal outer
חטאת, chatas, the blood doesn't go into the inner sanctum, okay, לא
חובה ולא מצוה lo chova velo mitzva for no purpose, not an
obligation, not a standing obligation, not a periodic type of a thing,
okay, nevertheless טעון יסוד, taun yesod, you spill it at the base.
מי שנכנס דמו לפנים בין לחובה בין למצוה, mi she'nichnas damo lifnim
bein le'chova bein le'mitzva, something like a פר כהן משיח par kohen
mashiach that the blood does go in the inner sanctum for whatever
reason, whether it's a strict standing obligation like יום כיפור Yom Kippur
or whether it's because
when it happens like פר כהן משיח, par kohen mashiach, anyway, but
if though, but if a normal outer חטאת chatas the blood is
at the base, an inner חטאת chatas how much more so.
אינו דין שטעון יסוד? eino din she'teun yesod? Okay, so therefore I
would have known it from a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. And if
I would have known that this כהן משיח kohen mashiach from a
קל וחומר kal vachomer is at the base, and nevertheless the verse
says to do it, maybe that's a doubling and maybe that's מעכב.
me'akev.
יכול יעכבנו? yachol ye'akvenu? Maybe it's מעכב. me'akev. תלמוד לומר talmud lomar
ואת כל הדם ישפך ve'es kol hadam yishapech I think ואת כל
דם הפר ישפך, ve'es kol dam hapar yishapech, נתקו הכתוב לעשה ועשאו
שירי מצוה, nitka hakasuv le'aseh ve'asahu sheyarei mitzva, לומר לך שיריים אין
מעכבין. lomar lach sheyarei ein me'akvin. It's telling you it's not מעכב.
me'akev. Why is it telling you it's not מעכב? me'akev? Because רש"י
Rashi says if you look at the earlier parts of the verse,
if the earlier parts of the verse are just one verb after
another verb. Okay, the earlier parts of the verse are, what does
it say? It says ולקח מדם הפר ve'lakach midam hapar והזה באצבעו
vehiza be'etzba'o ונתן על קרנות המזבח. venatan al karnos hamizbe'ach. Okay, it's
just verb, verb, verb. And when it got to this, it could
have said
ושפך את הדם אל יסוד המזבח, veshafach et hadam el yesod hamizbeach,
just another verb in a list of verbs. But it didn't. Okay,
after it says ולקח, velakach, והזה, vehizah, ונתן, venatan, it says, "Oh,
and by the way, as far as the blood is concerned, spill
that out." Okay, so it breaks the rhythm of the verbs to
tell you this is some secondary thing, this is some wrap-up thing,
it's not central to the act. Very interesting sort of read of
the grammar or of the style of the verse. Okay, so that's
how you know that even though you could have learned from a
קל וחומר kal vachomer you spill it, and you could say the
by saying it explicitly, it's telling you it's מעכב, meakev, by the
sort of style in which it's said, it's telling you it's not
מעכב. meakev. So here you have an explicit ברייתא braita where רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael is saying, whether it is the blood of the
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, whether it is the blood of פר כהן
משיח, par kohen mashiach, even the blood of the inner חטאות, chataot,
and even though yes, you're required to spill it at the base,
both based on a קל וחומר kal vachomer and a פסוק, pasuk,
it is not מעכב. meakev. So that proves רב פפא'ס Rav Pappa's
point that whatever רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
are debating about, maybe they're debating about whether the squeezing of the
blood of the bird is מעכב, meakev, but they're not debating about
the spilling of the blood of an inner חטאת. chatas. That they
agree is not מעכב. meakev. Okay.
So now, if that's true, let's go and discuss the bird issue.
Is that really being debated, whether that's
מעכב? meakev? וסבר רבי
ישמעאל מיצוי חטאת העוף מעכב? vesavar Rabbi Yishmael mitzuy chatas haof meakev?
Okay, fine, so good, you've done a nice job demonstrating that the
spilling of the blood is not מעכב meakev of an inner חטאת.
chatas. Are we now to believe though that he says the squeezing
of the blood of a bird חטאת chatas is מעכב? meakev? והתנא
דבי רבי ישמעאל, vehatana dbei Rabbi Yishmael, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael teaches
a ברייתא braita from the house of רבי ישמעאל: Rabbi Yishmael: והנשאר
בדם ימצה, vehanishar badam yimatze,
what's left of the blood of the bird in the bird, you
squeeze out, you press against the altar and squeeze it out. והנשאר
ימצה, vehanishar yimatze,
if there's anything left, then squeeze it out. ואינו נשאר לא ימצה,
veaino nishar lo yimatze, if there's nothing left, don't squeeze it out,
which one could say is a tautology, but but the point is
is that fine, it's you do it if you if it's possible
to do, which means now you could say, "Fine, but if it's
possible maybe it's מעכב." meakev. But since the point is that sometimes
it's not going to happen if there's no blood left over, then
he's basically saying implicitly the point is this procedure is not מעכב.
meakev. It's to be done if necessary, if it's around, but whether
there is extra blood or not extra blood, it's not מעכב. meakev.
So how can you say he says it is? So the גמרא
Gemara says תרי תנאי אליבא דרבי ישמעאל, trei tanaei aliba deRabbi Yishmael,
fine, it's a debate within רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael whether he says
it's מעכב meakev or not. Fine. So now we have said that
both רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael agree that
the spilling of the blood of an inner חטאת chatas is not
מעכב, meakev, although all other aspects of an inner חטאת chatas is
מעכב, meakev, every single application of blood on the פרוכת, parochet, on
the מזבח mizbeach and so on is מעכב, meakev, as opposed again,
remember an outer חטאת chatas just one application is מעכב, meakev, so
clearly the spilling it will not be, but by an inner חטאת
chatas all the applications are מעכב, meakev, so you could have thought
that the spilling is does prevent it from being good and here
we're saying no, whether according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva or רבי
ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, the spilling at the base, even if you don't
do it, the חטאת chatas is still valid, even in an inner
חטאת. chatas. But now we're going to say that there is an
opinion that says it is מעכב. meakev. Okay, because we've mentioned this
before, that although it's not in our משנה, Mishna, and although it's
not רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, the גמרא'ס
Gemara's going to say that there is an opinion that it is
מעכב. meakev. So let's take a look. אמר
רמי בר חמא האי תנא סבר שיריים מעכבי, amar Rami bar Chama
hai tana savar shirayim meakvi, the following תנא tana does hold that
the spilling of the remnant of the blood for an inner חטאת
chatas is מעכב. meakev. דתניא, detanya, we return to a ברייתא: braita:
הכהן המחטא אותה, hakohen himechate osah, the כהן kohen that does the
חטוי, chituy, does the making of the חטאת, chatas, does the atoning
of the חטאת, chatas, it says יאכלנה, yochelena, eats it, okay. So
that's basically telling you who's entitled to eat from a חטאת, chatas,
only a כהן kohen that's doing that, in theory could do the
עבודה, avodah, only a male כהן. kohen. Okay, that's what we're going
to get into the next משנה. Mishna. But our focus is going
to be what on the אותה, osah, that you do it this
way, the exact way it was said. Okay, so here's the ברייתא:
braita: אותה, osah, the חטאת chatas שניתן דמה למעלה, shenitan damah lemala,
if you did it as was instructed, you put the blood of
the חטאת chatas this is a normal outer חטאת. chatas. Okay, if
you put the blood at the on the top of the altar,
by the horns, okay, then it's a כשר kosher חטאת. chatas. ולא
אותה שניתן דמה למטה, velo osah shenitan damah lemata, if you put
the blood at the lower half of the altar, it's not a
valid חטאת. chatas. That we're learning from the word
אותה. osah. Now, ולא שניתן velo shenitan we'll see, we're going to
circle back and we'll see how this is relevant to the issue
of שיריים. shirayim. Now,
אמרת וכי מאין באת, amarta vechi meayin bata, what would have made
you think that it would have been valid if you had done
it at the lower half of the altar? Why did you need
a פסוק pasuk to tell me not? Because of the following: מכלל
ש... michlal she... And since it says ודם זבחיך ישפך על מזבח
יסוד העולה והבשר
תאכל v’dam zvachecha yishapech al mizbeach yesod ha’olah vehabasar tochal or תאכל,
tochel, spill the spill the blood at the base and eat the
meat. But that’s an interesting basis. Normally we learned it in the
beginning of the previous פרק perek from a different place. But since
here this is saying the principle that by a חטאת, chatas, an
outer חטאת, chatas, even one application of blood בדיעבד bediavad suffices even
though it’s supposed to be all four. How do you know it?
So from this it learns it from a generic verse that says
spill the blood at the base. Now even though that’s talking about
spilling the blood, we’re going to learn that to refer to any
application of blood makes it valid, okay, by all
sacrifices. Okay, anyway that’s, or at least by a חטאת. chatas. So
bracket that that verse because that’s not the verse we learned it
from before. But the basic point is we know that by a
חטאת chatas even one application of blood makes it valid, even if
you didn’t do all four. למנו לנתנו במתן ארבע שנתנו במתן אחת
כיפר. le’mno le’nitnu be’matan arba shenatnu be’matan achas kiper. So even by
a חטאת chatas that’s supposed to be all four corners if you
did just one you were יוצא. yotzei. יכול
אף הניתנים למעלה שנתנם למטה כיפר. yachol af hanitnim lemala shenatnam lemata
kiper. Now maybe this is the הוה אמינא hava amina that I
needed the word אותה osa to exclude. Once you’re showing me a
certain amount of latitude, it could be one of the four, it
doesn’t have to be all four, maybe if I just skipped the
horns altogether, maybe if I did the application at the lower half
the altar, maybe that’s good. ודין
הוא, v’din hu, and here would be the argument to say not
that way actually. נאמרו דמים למעלה ונאמרו דמים למטה. ne’emru damim lemala
vene’emru damim lemata. No, maybe I would say no. Forget the word,
the verse אותה. osa. I should logically know that even though I
have a certain amount of latitude, it’s not going to work if
I do it below. Why? Because there’s some blood that’s put above
and some that’s put below. So for example in the חטאת chatas
world, I mean in an עולה olah world, the עולה’s olah put
below but in a חטאת chatas world, the חטאת העוף chatas ha’of
the blood goes below. So מה דמים האמורים למטה שנתנם למעלה לא
כיפר, mah damim ha’amurim lemata shenatnam lemala lo kiper, we’re taking for
granted why it’s not clear based on other verses or whatever. We’re
taking for granted that blood that belongs on the lower half it
doesn’t work if you put it on the upper half. Okay so
if you did a חטאת העוף chatas ha’of on the upper half
it’s no good. So if that’s true even without the אותה osa
I should say if the lower half doesn’t work on the upper
half, the upper half doesn’t work on the lower half. אף דמים
האמורים למעלה שנתנם למטה לא כיפר. af damim ha’amurim lemala shenatnam lemata
lo kiper. So from there I could know that if you did
the blood on the lower half it’s not good. אם אמרת בתחתונים
שנתנם בנתינה למעלה שאין סופן למעלה לא כיפר. im amarta batachtonim shenatnam
b’netina lemala she’ein sofan lemala lo kiper. The bottom blood if you
put it on the top, you know why it doesn’t work? Because
the blood that if you did it in the right place at
the bottom it would never get to the top. Gravity doesn’t work
in reverse. So that’s why the top is considered completely irrelevant to
the bottom blood and that’s why bottom blood at the top doesn’t
work. תאמר בעליונים שנתנם למטה, tomar be’elyonim shenatnam lemata, but maybe top
blood maybe that would work if you put that it below. Why?
שכן סופן למטה, shekein sofan lemata, in the end top of the
blood eventually due to gravity does find its way to the bottom.
So since blood at the top does find its way to the
bottom, שיש מהן קריב דמים למטה, she’yesh mehen kariv damim lemata, so
therefore I might have thought that top חטאת chatas blood could work
at the bottom. Okay, so that’s why we needed the word אותה.
osa. You needed the word אותה osa to tell you since you’ve
already demonstrated a certain amount of latitude by a חטאת chatas that
one application is enough and since blood at the top eventually finds
its way to the bottom maybe if you put it at the
bottom you’re יוצא. yotzei. That was why you needed the word אותה.
osa. But now the ברייתא braita continues and it says the following:
it says it says but ששיריים פנימיים יוכיחו. she’shirayim pnimiyim yochi’chu. One
minute. You can't make that argument that since some of the blood
is going to get there maybe it should be good לכתחילה. l’chatchila.
I will show you stuff that will eventually get to a certain
place but it's not good if you started it at that place.
What’s the case? The blood of an inner חטאת. chatas. The blood
of an inner חטאת, chatas, the leftover blood eventually gets where? To
the base of the outer altar. But if you were to try
to put לכתחילה l’chatchila the blood of an inner חטאת chatas on
the outer altar, it obviously wouldn’t be good. So although some of
the blood eventually gets somewhere else does not mean that that’s a
legitimate place to put the blood. Okay, so if that’s true about
the blood in the inner altar that the remnant goes to the
base but don’t go ahead and put לכתחילה l’chatchila the blood of
the inner altar on the outer altar, so therefore here too just
because the blood that you put at the top eventually runs down
does not mean that you could have start by putting the blood
at the base at or you know at the bottom half. Okay,
so שיש מהן קריב בחוץ she’yesh mehen kariv bachutz if you think
about the inner חטאת chatas that some of that blood goes on
the outer altar, the remnant of the blood, ואם נתנם בתחילה בחוץ
לא כיפר v’im netnam betchila bachutz lo kiper and if you put
them initially on the outside it’s not valid. You started though at
the outside, it wasn't good. So therefore, because of that, don't try
to make a הוה אמינא, hava amina, an argument, oh, I need
a פסוק אותה pasuk osah to tell me don't put the blood
of the חטאת chatas at the bottom half, because I would have
thought you would because it eventually runs there anyway. Okay. The blood
of an inner חטאת, chatas, some of it gets to the outer
and that's the outer is not good. So there's no הוה אמינא
hava amina to say something like that. גמרא Gemara says, yes there
is, לא, lo, no, it's not a good comparison. I would say
that even though that's true about an inner חטאת, chatas, that by
the outer חטאת, chatas, since the blood runs to the bottom, maybe
the bottom is good. Why? לא. lo. אם אמרת בדמים הפנימיים, im
amarta bedamim hapnimim, when you come to the inner blood שאין מזבח
הפנימי ממרקן, she'ein mizbeach hapnimi memarkan, the inner altar doesn't cleanse them,
doesn't finish them. You're not done with the inner altar. תאמר בעליונים
שהרי קרניו ממרקות אותן, tomar ba'elyonim sheharei karnav memarkos osan, but by
the outer altar, the horns do finish them. What does that mean?
אם נתן למטה כשרים, im nasan lemata kesherim, so maybe they would
be כשרים kesherim if you put at the bottom. תלמוד לומר אותה,
Talmud lomar osah, that's what אותה osah teaches you. אותה שניתן דמים
למעלה ולא שניתן דמים למטה, osah shenissan damim lemala velo shenissan damim
lemata, you only have to put that, no, a חטאת chatas can
only be put above not below. So what is this difference about
does the inner altar finish them or not? So we're going to
say the following, what this ברייתא Braisa means is the following. When
you put the blood at the inner altar, you're not done. Why
are you not done? What do you have to do with the
remnant? You have to pour it at the base. So we're going
to think that what that means is, not just because obviously we
know everything you have to remnant you have to pour at the
base, that's not a difference between inner and outer. But the point
is like this, we're going to assume, we're going to read this
ברייתא Braisa to assume that it means that the spilling of the
blood for an inner חטאת chatas is מעכב. me'akeiv. So the argument
goes like this. Here the reason if you put the blood starts
here and ends at the outer base. But it's obvious you can't
just start at the outer base. Why? Because basically, now you might
realize you would say the opposite, but follow this, because this is
weightier. Why is this weightier? It's weighty because the putting the blood
here isn't the whole story. The remnant of the blood requires and
is מעכב me'akeiv if you don't put it there. So because the
putting of the blood in that place you're not done with it
and it's weighty, then there is more limit to what you can
do with that blood and you can't start it at the base
because it's not just even enough to put it here, you have
to put it here and to be יוצא yotzei you have to
put it at the base as well. That's by the inner one.
But goes the argument, by the outer one, if you start up
here, okay, you're done when you did that first application of blood.
Rather even if you only did one horn and you didn't do
the other horns, even if you only did one horn and you
didn't pour at the base, you're still יוצא. yotzei. Since you're still
יוצא, yotzei, we see the blood of the outer altar has much
more latitude, right? One application is enough. And since it's much more
latitude, I might think that since the blood runs to the bottom
you can start by putting it at the bottom. Okay? So the
argument is like this. Because the blood runs to the bottom, I
would have thought you could start by putting it there. You needed
the word, the verse אותה osah to tell me you can't. You're
going to tell me no, just because blood ends somewhere you can't
start by doing it. And the evidence to that is the inner
חטאת. chatas. My answer to you is the inner חטאת chatas has
more limit. How do I know the inner חטאת chatas has more
limit? Because you're not even done when you're done with the inner
מזבח. mizbeach. It still requires that you spill it at the base
and that's still מעכב. me'akeiv. So because of those limits, you're not
allowed to start at the end. But because this has fewer limits,
one application is enough, maybe you're allowed to start at the end
and you're allowed to start by doing it at the base. That's
the הוה אמינא. hava amina. So buried in that whole הוה אמינא
hava amina argument, which anyway in the end we reject להלכה, l'halacha,
buried in that is an assumption that here when you do the
corner you're done, and here when you do the inner altar you're
not done, it's still מעכב me'akeiv to do it at the base.
Okay? So that proves that this תנא Tanna holds that the base
is מעכב me'akeiv by the inner חטאת. chatas. Is he suggesting within
this argument that if you start at the base you'd still have
to put it at least one on top or not? No, just
start. Since that's where the blood is going to end and since
you have more latitude here, even one application is enough and all
you need is to apply it at the horns and you don't
need to do anything else, so since this Torah gives you more
latitude, maybe you could just forget about the horns and just start
it at the lower half. It's a funny הוה אמינא. hava amina.
But what interests us is that it says here you're not done
and here you're done. So here you're not done by the inner
חטאת chatas means it's understood to mean that the spilling at the
base
is מעכב. me'akeiv. So
let's take a look. מאי, mai, what's meant by מאי שאין מזבח
הפנימי ממרקן? mai she'ein mizbeach hapnimi memarkan? What does it mean that
the inner altar does not finish them? Okay, לאו, lav, doesn't it
not mean אלו שיריים, elu shiriem, that the remnants are still מעכב?
me'akeiv? So you see... least the author of this ברייתא braisa holds
that the remnants are מעכב. m'akeiv. So אמר ליה רבא, amar lei
Rava, so רבא Rava says no, if that's what it meant, the
argument would have been the exact opposite. It would have been a
terrible argument. אי הכי, ei hachi, תיתי בקל וחומר, teisei be'kal vachomer,
the קל וחומר kal vachomer would have gone the opposite way. מה
שיריים הפנימיים שסופן חובה בחוץ ma shiyarei hapenimiyim she'sofan chova bachutz עשאן
בתחילה בחוץ לא כיפר, asan bitchila bachutz lo kipeir, no, actually it
would have been a better argument that the bottom doesn't work here.
Because if here, by the inner חטאת, chatas, although it's required to
go on the outer, and the outer is an essential part of
making it valid, and nevertheless the outer base, it doesn't work to
start at the outer base, so here where pouring at the base
is not מעכב, m'akeiv, how much more so should you not be
allowed to start at the base? So if the comparison is that
here the base is required and here not, then if anything that
strengthens the point that you would have said that you don't need
the word אותה osah and that you would have been obvious that
the base you can't start at the base. If you can't start
at the base by an inner חטאת chatas where the base is
a required part of the process, how much more so should you
not be able to start it by an outer חטאת chatas where
it's not a required part of the process? So they're not really
saying when they say start they really mean finish right? Well right
meaning that the whole עבודה. avoda. It's invalid if he had poured
some blood on the outer for the inner חטאת, chatas, first he
poured some at the base and then went inside. Yeah that wouldn't
ruin it right by start I mean that's the whole עבודה avoda
correct. Yeah okay so אם תאמר, im tomar, if anything if that's
true then you don't need the verse אותה. osah. The קל וחומר
kal vachomer makes it clear that you shouldn't be able to do
the עבודה avoda at the bottom I'll say it that way okay?
מה שיריים הפנימיים שסופן חובה בחוץ ma shiyarei hapenimiyim she'sofan chova bachutz
עשאן בתחילה, asan bitchila, I'm using the word בתחילה bitchila that's what
sort of why I said beginning but meaning that the whole עבודה
avoda if you focus that בחוץ לא כיפר bachutz lo kipeir it's
not good. הניתן למעלה שאין סופן חובה למטה, hanitan l'ma'ala she'ein sofan
chova l'mata, the stuff that's above by an outer חטאת chatas that
there's no requirement I mean you're supposed to but it's not necessary
to do it at the base. עשאן בתחילה למטה asan bitchila l'mata
if there you did the עבודה avoda at the base and that
was all you did, אינו דין שלא כיפר eino din she'lo kipeir
certainly it's no good. So obviously when it's trying to say oh
here maybe you can't start at the base or you can't do
the עבודה avoda at the base but here you can it's not
it cannot be that it's assumed that here it's מעכב m'akeiv and
here it's not מעכב m'akeiv at the base. If anything then that
would be more of a reason to prove that if it doesn't
work here at the base it doesn't work here at the base
if it's מעכב. m'akeiv. So that's not the point of this ברייתא.
braisa. So what is the point that here you're not done when
you do the inner altar and here you are done? It has
nothing to do with the base says רבא. Rava. So רבא Rava
says the following: אלא אין מזבח הפנימי מעכב מכאן בלבד אלא פרוכת.
ela ein mizbei'ach hapenimi m'akeiv mikan bilvad ela paroches. There's a much
easier read of that. It means it's not just about the inner
altar it's also about the curtain. Okay so all we're trying to
point out is that here it's weightier but we don't want to
give weight to the base what we want to say is like
this: here it's weightier first also what you could have just said
is it's weightier because you need all applications if you miss any
application it's no good. Here you need all applications and it's not
just being applied one place it's being applied two places the altar
and the פרוכת. paroches. So in that case if you just started
at the base whatever you just did the base it would be
no good whereas here on the outer altar it only has one
place you're putting it the altar nowhere else and one application suffices.
So here I might have thought there's more latitude and you could
go to the bottom okay but anyway it has nothing to do
with whether the spilling of the שיריים shiyarei is מעכב m'akeiv that
is a complete distraction if anything that would have made the argument
in the opposite direction okay? Now תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. We now
we're still going to try to see if maybe there is somebody
that holds that the spilling of the שיריים shiyarei by an inner
חטאת chatas is מעכב. m'akeiv. Let's take a look. תנו רבנן, tanu
rabanan, וכילה מכפר v'chila m'kapeir this is again by יום כיפור Yom
Kippur where if you're done with the atonements then you're done. אם
כיפר כילה ואם לא כיפר לא כילה דברי רבי עקיבא. im kipeir
chila v'im lo kipeir lo chila divrei Rabbi Akiva. רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says if you did the atonements which means presumably the applications
of blood not the spilling of the blood which isn't mentioned there
and isn't considered a כפרה kapara then you're done. Okay if you
haven't done all the applications you're not done. So obviously so the
basic חידוש chiddush being two points I guess number one is that
all the applications are מעכב m'akeiv by an inner חטאת chatas and
by יום כיפור Yom Kippur and number two that the שיריים shiyarei
is not מעכב m'akeiv okay? That's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says.
אמר לו רבי יהודה. amar lo Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
said to him: מפני מה לא נאמר mipnei ma lo ne'emar why
not say the following: אם כילה כיפר אם לא כילה לא כיפר.
im chila kipeir im lo chila lo kipeir. Rather than saying if
you atoned you're done say if you're done you atoned. Now what's
the difference? So if you atoned you're done says we're focusing only
on the things that are labeled as acts of atonement. If you're
done you're done okay if you're done you've atoned means maybe it's
not limited to the things that are labeled as acts of atonement.
So that's going to have the possibility of including the idea of
what do you call it of this filling of the שיריים, shirayim,
at least according to one reading. So let's take a look. אם
כילה כיפר אם לא כילה לא כיפר, Im kila kiper, im lo
kila lo kiper, אם חיסר אחת מכל המתנות לא עשה ולא כלום.
Im chisair achas m'kol hamatanos lo asa v'lo klum. If you didn't
do one of the applications of blood, you weren't יוצא. yotze. All
of the applications are מעכב. meakev. Okay, which we know by an
inner חטאת. chatas. So מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? What are they debating?
One says if you atoned you're done, and the other says if
you're done you atoned. What's the debate? So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
and רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, these אמוראים Amoraim
debate the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. חד אמר משמעות דורשין איכא בינייהו. Chad amar mashma'os darsheen eika
beinaihu. Yeah, they're not really debating any הלכה, halacha, just whether you
start with the word atone or do you start with the word
done. וחד אמר, V'chad amar, the other says, שיריים מעכבין איכא בינייהו.
shirayim meakvin eika beinaihu. Ah, so now we finally are getting to
an idea that one תנא Tanna holds that by an inner חטאת
chatas the spilling of the שיריים shirayim is מעכב. meakev. If you
say if you atoned you're done, it's only the acts that are
labeled as acts of atonement, it's only the application of blood. That's
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. But according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, if
you say when you're done you've atoned, means when you're done with
everything. So you also require the spilling of the שיריים. shirayim. So
now the גמרא Gemara says תסתיים דרבי יהושע בן לוי הוא דאמר
שיריים מעכבי. tistayaim d'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi hu d'amar shirayim meakvi. So
of this debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי יהושע בן
לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, let's try to conclude that it's רבי
יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi who says that there's a
תנא Tanna that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda holds that the spilling of
the שיריים shirayim is מעכב. meakev. Why? דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי,
D'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, לדברי האומר שיריים מעכבין, l'divrei ha'omer shirayim
meakvin, because he says the following thing: according to that תנא Tanna
that holds that שיריים shirayim are מעכב, meakev, what would happen on
יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? By the way, we don't know if he
would say it by a normal inner חטאת chatas or is he
just saying it by יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. יום כיפור Yom Kippur
is possibly the weightiest. Okay, but anyway, he says what would happen
if when you are going to spill the remnant of the blood
on the outer altar, you tripped and it spilled on the floor?
Okay, or something happened. So now you have—that's מעכב, meakev, you need
to get more blood to do. But how do you get more
blood? You can שחט shecht another goat or another calf, but then
you have blood of a goat but it's not the שיריים. shirayim.
If the הלכה halacha is the remnant has to be spilled, then
this isn't remnant. This is original blood, it's not leftover. Okay. So
what would you do if the שיריים shirayim is מעכב meakev and
you spilled the שיריים? shirayim? How would you get more? So he
says: לדברי האומר שיריים מעכבין מביא פר אחד ומתחיל בתחילה בפנים. L'divrei
ha'omer shirayim meakvin maivi par echad umaschil betchila bifnim. Yeah, you'd have
to do the inner עבודה avoda again—not the inner-inner, not the, you
know, כפורת kaporet or whatever, but you'd have to do the עבודה
avoda of the מזבח, mizbe'ach, you'd have to do that again in
order so that the remainder would be considered remainder. In order to
create remainder you have to שחט shecht a calf, do some of
the מתנות matanos in the inner sanctum again, so that now you
can have remainder to spill at the base. Anyway, what's interesting for
us is that he acknowledges that there's an opinion that says שיריים
shirayim is מעכב. meakev. So presumably רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi is the one that says that's the debate of רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, and רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says שיריים shirayim is מעכב. meakev. So the גמרא Gemara says
אטו רבי יוחנן לית ליה האי סברא? Atu Rabbi Yochanan lais lei
hai sevara? What, you think רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan doesn't hold that
somebody holds—that there's someone out there that holds שיריים shirayim is מעכב?
meakev? I'll show you he does. דאמר רבי יוחנן תנא רבי נחמיה
כדברי האומר שיריים מעכבין. D'amar Rabbi Yochanan tana Rabbi Nechemia k'divrei ha'omer
shirayim meakvin. That רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemia who teaches a particular ברייתא,
braisa, okay, that if you brought remnant of blood and you did
it as an עבודה avoda out of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
you're חייב chayav for doing עבודה בחוץ. avoda bachutz. So רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says well he's following the opinion that the שיריים shirayim
is מעכב. meakev. And since this remnant of blood is required to
do as a required עבודה avoda in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
you're liable if you use it as an עבודה avoda out of
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So this again recognizes that there's some
תנא Tanna out there that holds that the remnant of the blood,
at least by an inner חטאת, chatas, is מעכב. meakev. So how
could they be debating whether that's the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda if they both agree that there
is a תנא Tanna that holds that שיריים shirayim is מעכב? meakev?
So the גמרא Gemara says אלא כדברי האומר ולאו להני תנאי. Ella
k'divrei ha'omer v'lav lehani tannai. One of these, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
or רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, holds there's some
תנא Tanna out there that holds שיריים shirayim is מעכב, meakev, but
they're not claiming that that's what the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda are. Just because that's—just because they
acknowledge that there's some תנא Tanna that holds it doesn't mean that
we're saying that that's the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. הכא נמי כדברי האומר ולאו להני תנאי. Hacha
nami k'divrei ha'omer v'lav lehani tannai. So what we have concluded is
that both רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi concede that like Holy Grail that we were looking
for for the last two days, that although that there is a
תנא Tanna that holds at least by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, okay,
we're not and certainly not by the outer חטאת. chatas. חטאות. chataos.
At least by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, maybe by the other inner
חטאות, chataot, hold that the שייריים shiyaraim is מעכב. me'akev. They both
hold that. And then there's interesting נפקא מינהs, nafka mina if you
use that שייריים shiyaraim to do an עבודה avoda out of the
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you would be חייב chayav according to that
opinion. If you spilled the שייריים shiyaraim on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
what would you do to generate new שייריים? shiyaraim? They both hold
that there is a תנא tana out there that holds it, and
according to one of them, that's actually the debate of רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva and רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. That when רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says when you're done, you've atoned, not when you're atoned you've
done, but when you're done you've atoned, that's the opinion that שייריים
shiyaraim is מעכב. me'akev. So there genuinely is a תנא tana out
there that holds שייריים shiyaraim is מעכב, me'akev, maybe it's this debate
of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, but whoever
it is, there is that opinion at least by יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, maybe by all of the inner חטאות. chataos. Okay, so now
we are done with the משנה mishna looking at the issue of
the inner חטאת, chatas, what are all the פסוקים psukim we learn
it from, and whether the שייריים shiyaraim is מעכב, me'akev, that is
the story of the inner חטאת. chatas. All the applications are מעכב,
me'akev, is שייריים shiyaraim מעכב, me'akev, that's a debate. Let's now start
the next משנה. mishna. Did we make a conclusion about that question?
Nope. Nope. Okay. חטאות הציבור והיחיד. Chataos hatzibbur vehayachid. Now we move
from an inner חטאת chatas to a regular חטאת. chatas. Okay, regular
חטאת, chatas, whether it's a communal one like as
we'll see in a minute brought on the רגלים regalim
or on ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, or whether it's a personal one,
okay, what's the הלכה halacha of a normal regular outer חטאת? chatas?
אלו הן חטאות הציבור, Elu hein chataos hatzibbur, first let's list them:
שעירי ראשי חדשים ושל מועדות. se'irei roshei chodashim veshamo'ados. Communal חטאות chataos
that are not inner ones, the inner ones are like יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, פר כהן משיח. par kohen mashiach. This is a communal
outer חטאת, chatas, it's the normal you know שעיר אחד לחטאת se'ir
echad l'chatas that we bring on every ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh and
on every יום טוב Yom Tov in the מוסף. Musaf. Now all
these things, whether they're communal or private, they're outer חטאות. chataos. שחיטתן
בצפון, Shechitatan batzafon, you slaughter them at the north of the altar.
וקיבול דמן בכלי שרת בצפון, Vekibul daman bichli sharet batzafon, you catch
their blood in a holy vessel in the north, which means that
the catching has to be in the north and the vessel has
to be in the north and the person has to be in
the north. By שחיטה, shechita, the person doesn't have to be in
the north. By the way, something I failed to mention earlier, תוספות
Tosfos raises an interesting point that why does it say כלי שרת
kli sharet specifically by catching the blood and it doesn't say it
by שחיטה? shechita? Okay, now he says that just might be a
stylistic thing. Since by the כלי kli by the catching of the
blood we wanted to say the catching itself has to be in
the north and the vessel has to be in the north, we
mentioned that it's a כלי שרת. kli sharet. Whereas by שחיטה shechita
as we know, the person could be standing in the south, most
of the knife could be in the south, I guess if you
get enough of the knife into you know to cut the neck
and so on. But so it just might be stylistic because the
person and the knife can be in the south, so we're not
mentioning the knife. But תוספות Tosfos does raise the question: does the
knife that you use for שחיטה shechting a קרבן korban have to
be a כלי שרת? kli sharet? Fascinating question, right? שחיטה Shechting doesn't
have to be done by a כהן, kohen, the guy doesn't have
to be standing in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, let alone in
the north. So if that's true, maybe you don't even need a
כלי שרת, kli sharet, maybe the knife doesn't even have to be
sanctified. So תוספות Tosfos has a whole discussion whether that's true or
not. Anyway, so I just wanted to mention that. So that's in
terms of the חטאת, chatat, it's all in the north. ודמן טעון
ארבע מתנות על ארבע קרנות. Vedaman te'un arbah matanot al arbah kranot.
As opposed to the inner חטאות chataot where it has you know
the פרוכת paroches and the and the golden altar, this is the
four corners of the outer altar. Okay, and as we know, as
we've been saying, בדיעבד bedieved even one you're יוצא. yotzei. כיצד, Keitzad,
now how would you do it? עולה בכבש, Oleh bakevesh, you go
up on the ramp. Okay, here you go up the ramp, the
ramp is in the south. Okay, ופונה לסובב, ufoneh lasovev, you turn
on the walkaround. The סובב sovev is the walkaround that it exists
like if here are the horns, okay, and then there's like a
walkaround here where you can stand, the כהן kohen stands and it
walks around. I don't know if it's anyway and therefore it allows
them to apply the stuff on the horns and that's called the
סובב. sovev. Now he's going up on the on the on the
ramp. Now when he gets to the turns off on the walkaround,
okay, he's going to basically go like this. He's going to go
counterclockwise. This is how come the bride when she walks around the
groom goes counterclockwise, also has to do with how we take the
ספר תורה Sefer Torah out of the ארון. aron. The point is
you're always moving to your right. You're facing the center and you're
moving to your right. Okay, so if you think about when the
person comes out of the ארון, aron, takes the ספר תורה Sefer
Torah out of the ארון, aron, if he's facing the בימה, bima,
right, and he's going to move towards his right, he's going to
move counterclockwise. That's the basic principle that כל פינות שאתה פונה לא
יהא אלא לימינה. kol pinos she'ata poneh lo yehei ela leyamina. Okay,
same thing, the bride faces the groom and then she goes counterclockwise,
goes to her right. So that's what's going to happen here. You're
going to go up and then you're going to go to your
right. So you're going to start with the southeast corner, you're going
to go southeast, northeast, northwest, southwest, and that's how you're going to
hit all four corners. ובא לו לקרן דרומית מזרחית Uba lo lekeren
dromis mizrachis southeast, מזרחית צפונית mizrachis tzonis northeast, צפונית מערבית tzonis ma'aravis
northwest, מערבית דרומית ma'aravis dromis southwest. You did all four corners. שירי
הדם היה שופך ליסוד דרומי. Shiyarei hadam haya shofech l'yesod dromi. Come
down the ramp. Now as opposed to with the blood from the
inner חטאות chataot that you did on the west base, okay, because
that was the one you hit first, okay, here you're going to
do it on the south base, because when you come down the
ramp, the closest base you're next to, if you're coming down from
the southwest side but the ramp is on the south, you're closest
to the south base. So you're going to spill the blood at
the south base, not at the west base. ונאכלים לפנים מן הקלעים.
V'nechalim bifnim min haklaim. It's eaten inside the curtains, means in the
עזרה, Azarah, curtains evoking the idea of the משכן, Mishkan, that you
had the curtain surrounding the courtyard. It's eaten inside the courtyard, the
Temple courtyard, not in the עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim, up to the
עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim, עזרת ישראל. Ezrat Yisrael. לזכרי כהונה, L'zichrei kehuna,
by male כהנים, Kohanim, okay, even if they're בעלי מומים. baalei mumim.
בכל מאכל, B'chol ma'achal, in any form of eating, meaning it doesn't
have to be roasted, it's not a קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. ליום
ולילה עד חצות, L'yom valaila ad chatzot, for that day that it
was brought and the following night, really it could be eaten the
whole night, but as the first משנה Mishna in ברכות Brachot teaches,
we told you to do it up to midnight so you wouldn't
get sloppy and then forget about finishing it up and so on.
So in principle it's the whole night, but we say only until
midnight, okay? We'll end with this today and we'll pick up on
the גמרא Gemara on this tomorrow.